Guide to the French Benevolent Society Records 1873-1976 MS 233
New-York Historical Society
French Benevolent Society records
1873-1976
New-York Historical Society
French Benevolent Society of New York
MS 233
2.5 Linear feet in two document boxes and nine standing volumes
The French Benevolent Society records contain an array of fiscal reports, administrative minutes, deeds, insurance policies, correspondence, and record books that predominately relate to the French Hospital, however some documents focus on the Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
This collection is organized by document genre/format into two boxes and nine freestanding volumes. Deeds and other documents were foldered together as found in their original packets in the records.
Biographical / Historical
The French Benevolent Society was founded in 1809 in New York City. The Society's mission was to provide charitable assistance to members of New York City's French community.
The Society founded the French Hospital in 1881. The hospital was originally located at 131 East 14th Street in New York City, but later moved to 330 West 30th Street. The hospital housed 255 beds and employed 850 people. The hospital closed in 1977 due to financial problems.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eugene Blanc and Ruth Granet, 1977.
Scope and Contents
(Note: Neither the processing nor supervising archivists for the collection could read French. Consequently, although the following note is complete as to overall content, it may not be complete as to particular important details if those were in the French language documents.)
The French Benevolent Society records contain an array of documents. A significant portion of the collection focuses upon the French Hospital, however, these papers are mainly financial and legal in nature.
The Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society minutes are held in nine volumes and cover much, but not the entire history, of the organization. The minutes include a variety of French Hospital topics such as: overall costs/losses, the creation of new medical departments, hospital supply rosters and costs, basic medical staff information, details about hospital capacities, donations, etc. The minutes also cover topics relating to the Society such as board elections, other charitable operations, member lists, and more. It should be noted that 6 out of the 9 volumes are written in French.
The content of Box 1 includes various documents including individual warranty deeds presented to the French Benevolent Society, deeds for hospital property, deeds for graves at Flushing Cemetery and Kensico Cemetery, papers relating to Mrs. Vizet and her plot/mausoleum at Woodlawn Cemetery, several loan agreements and tax documents between the French Benevolent Society and Emigrant Savings Bank, deeds for cemetery plots at Calvary, Greenwood, Rosehill, and St. Michael's Cemetery, as well as a collection of documents recounting the history of the French Hospital.
The second box contains a volume titled "Reservistes Livre No.1." This volume appears to be a financial ledger, however, it is mostly written in French and therefore solidly establishing its true purpose has been difficult. A basic format was noted within this volume where each page states the name of an individual or family, a short biography of the person(s) is provided at the top, and the rest of the page is filled with dates and payments.
Cemeteries; Emigration and immigration; Annual reports.; Deeds.; Indentures.; Minutes (administrative records); New York (N.Y.); Legal correspondence.; Personal correspondence; French Hospital (New York, N.Y.)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1873 March-1880 June (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 1)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1880 October-1883 October (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 2)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1893 November-1902 June (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 3)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1902 July-1914 October (Offsite-box FB-2, Volume 4)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1914 November-1923 October (Offsite-box FB-2, Volume 5)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1923 October-1932 September (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 6)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1932 October-1937 December (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 7)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1938 January-1945 December (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 8)
- Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Administration of the French Benevolent Society, 1946 January-1953 December (Offsite-box FB-1, Volume 9)
- Warranty Deeds, 1926 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The following deeds to the French Benevolent Society can be found in this folder: Mary Wood, Adolph and Rose Goldner, Harry and Ada Hirschfield, Ethol Realty Company Inc, Anna Binsky, Bella Bellucci, Camillo and Orsola Gilardino, and Joseph R. and Helen L. Potter.
- Deeds for Hospital Property (2 Folders), 1904-1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2a-b)
  The following materials can be found in folder a: survey maps of hospital property, French Benevolent Society (FBS) correspondence, receipt of funds notice from FBS to Bank, and legal correspondence with Delafield Marsh Porter and Hope.
  The following documents can be found in folder b: Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank Extension and Modification of Mortgages #16741, Contract of Sale between Hazkate Holding Corporation and French Benevolent Society, Warranty Deed from Albert Brown, Harry Brown, and Anna Brown, and Deed from Evelyn Mandeville, Caroline Mandeville Marks, and Henrietta Eliza Mandeville.
- Deeds for Graves. Flushing Cemetery, 1941, 1957 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder contains several certificates from Flushing Cemetery Association and Kenisco Cemetery to the French Benevolent Society regarding received payment of $65 for graves.
- Woodlawn Cemetery Supporting Papers, 1931-1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  The documents in this folder relate to Mrs. Louise Vizet, her grave/mausoleum allotment (#16899), and deed (#2963) at Woodlawn Cemetery. Documents include: a deed from Vizet to Woodlawn Cemetery, receipt of grave purchase and upkeep, and correspondence between Vizet and Woodlawn Cemetery.
- Mortgage and Loan Agreements, 1917, 1920-1928, 1934-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  This folder contains numerous financial documents including: correspondence with the French Benevolent Society, bond and mortgage notices from Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank, Department of Finance tax document, extension of mortgage from Emigrant Industrial Savings Bank, and water bills.
- Deeds - Cemetery Plots (Calvary, Greenwood, Rosehill, St. Michael's), 1883 -1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  Greenwood Cemetery Documents: Deed of Conveyance between Miss Maude Louise Troombly to Mr. Victor Vizet, Receipt of Conveyance between Miss Maude Louise Troombly to Mr. Victor Vizet, two Cast River National Bank Checks from Victor Vizet, memo describing Vizet papers, letter from French Hospital to Mr. Clarence A. Weill stating all documents related to Victor A. Vizet, Deed from Greenwood Cemetery to Miss Maud Louise Troombly.
  St. Michael's Cemetery Documents: license receipt from St. Michael's Cemetery for 3 residents, card of graves, and receipt of grave payment.
  Fairview Cemetery Documents: cemetery deed #1598 of plot payment ($20) for Albert Barbier, cemetery deed #1599 of plot payment ($25) for Albert Barbier, and note from Octave V. Monroy about Barbier graves.
  Calvary Cemetery Documents: grave deed for Mr. Vincent Fulchiron for Emma Marie Abel and Mollie McGrath Hale, correspondence between French Hospital Benevolent Society and Calvary and Allied Cemeteries regarding payment to maintain graves of Abel and Hale, permission to inter remains of Pierre Guillerm in free ground, and correspondence between Octave V. Monory and Vincent Fulchiron [French]
  Rosehill Cemetery: Single Grave Certificate
- French Hospital Background Materials, 1958-1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  The documents in this folder contain: Histoire des Sciences Medicales Journal, bibliography of materials relating to French Hospital exhibit displayed at NY Academy of Medicine, program cover for Bicentennial Exhibition at French Hospital, and centerfold providing history of French Hospital.
- Reservistes, Livre No. 1, 1914-1916 (Offsite-box 2)